# 江西·婺源
Wuyuan, Jiangxi
# 哈喽 雪鱼现在在江西婺源
Hello, Xueyu is in Wuyuan, Jiangxi now.
# 来这边呢 是为了去篁岭村看看这边的晒秋
The reason I am visiting here is to see the “Sai Qiu” (sun dry autumn veg) in Huanglin Village.
# 就是网上很火爆的那个 有晒南瓜的 晒辣椒的
It is very popular in internet, like sun-dry pumpkin, sun-dry chili
# 在去之前呢 一定要先把肚子填饱
Before departure, it’d better to eat something
# 因为你也不知道 到那边有没有卖吃的
Because you don’t know whether you can find restaurant there
# 这边比较特色的一种早餐 叫做汽糕
One of the special breakfast here, is call “Qi Gao” (steamed cake)
# 是我一直想尝试的 今天早上咱们去看看吧
I want to try it for a long time, so let’s take a look this morning.
# 真是太冷了
It is really cold.
# 现在就是 今年正式开始穿羽绒服的时候了
Now is the time for down jacket
# 他这边汽糕是6块钱一个
They sell one Qi Gao for 6 Rmb here.
# 没有人收款吗
No cashier?
# 哎呀 没看到人收款
Aya, there is no cashier.
# 自己付上钱 自己拿吧
Let me just pay and ask.
# 老板
# 来个汽糕
Lao Ban (owner, boss), one Qi Gao please.
# 我们是不是 应该在那边拿
Should we get it over there?
# 现在是做的新的一个
Now they are making a fresh one
# 阿姨 这个加的是黄豆芽吗  是的 还有梅干菜
Auntie, is this bean sprout? - Yes. - There are also dried mustard green.
# 阿姨 这一锅大约会蒸多久
Auntie, how long it take to make one like this?
# 这个没多久
Not long
# 几分钟吗？这个受火力大小影响
How many minutes? It depends on the heat.
# 一般几分钟蒸好
Usually just a couple of minutes
# 快的时候不到一分钟
Sometime it do not even take a minute.
# 我看当地有卖厚的和薄的汽糕是吧
I see there are thick one and thin one, is that right?
# 有什么样的区别
What’s the difference?
# 厚的汽糕就厚一点  更松软 其它都是一样的
Thick Qi Gao is thicker, fluffier. The rest is the same.
# 厚汽糕 发酵的时间也不一样
Thick Qi Gao, requires different fermentation time.
# 厚汽糕 有的人喜欢吃 有的人不喜欢吃
Thick Qi Gao, some people like, some don’t.
# 现在年轻人喜欢吃这种
Young people prefer this one. (Thin one)
# 老人家喜欢吃那个厚的  那个多 分量多
Senior like thick one, because of its large quantity.
# 而且味道好吃点
And taste better.
# 这边就是做的这种薄汽糕
There are making the thin Qi Gao here.
# 几乎不到一分钟就可以出一锅
Didn’t take a minute to make one.
# 这种做起来比较快一点
It is quicker to make
# 出锅之后还会加上辣椒油和葱花
After it is steamed, they will add chili oil and chopped green onion
# 坐哪里
Where do you want to seat?
# 随便就可以
Anywhere.
# 坐这儿吧 谢谢
Maybe here, thanks!
# 跋山涉水来到婺源 雪鱼要尝尝他们这边的汽糕
Take a long time to Wuyuan, Xueyu want to try this local food - Qi Gao.
# 这是要了一份6块钱的
This is one portion, 6 rmb.
# 上面呢 是加了梅干菜 黄豆芽
There are some dried mustard green and bean sprouts
# 出锅之后 还会抹上辣椒 撒上小葱花
When it is steamed, they will brush chili oil and sprinkle chopped green onion.
# 汽糕是用米浆做的 吃起来特别松软
Qi Gao is made from rice milk. It tastes very fluffy.
# 再来一口
One more bite.
# 汽糕的做法和广东的肠粉是很像的
The way they make Qi Gao is very similar to Cheung Fen from Guangdong.
# 你看 汽糕是把米浆舀到蒸屉上
See, they scoop the rice milk to the steamer rack
# 然后在米浆上 放上豆芽 梅干菜
And add bean sprout and dried green mustard
# 这么蒸出来的
And then steam.
# 还有 它这个汽糕吃起来是有微微的酸味
Qi Gao has a very subtle sour taste in it.
# 我问了一下 他们说这个
I asked (where the sourness come from), they told me that
# 做汽糕的米浆是用发酵的米浆做出来的
The rice milk is actually fermented.
# 吸取了上次在南昌的经验
I learnt my lesson in Nanchang (also a city in Jiangxi)
# 这次问我要辣的 还是要不辣的
They asked me whether I want it spicy or not.
# 我说要微辣就可以
I asked for mild spicy
# 在这边 辣的真的是吃不了
In here, “Spicy” is too much
# 在江西 辣的真的是吃不了
In Jiangxi, “Spicy” is too spicy for me
# 提前一晚定了门票：140元/人  坐索道来回
Booked the ticket the night before: 140 rmb per person, take cable car to there and return
# 熟悉的梯田 走在路上也都是风景
Familiar terrace, beautiful scenery along the way
# 人家都抱一个 你抱俩干什么
Other people only take one, why you take two?
# 短暂的旅行 为生活充个电
A short trip to recharge your life